<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Chewton 28 of July, 1658 VVhereas wee of the mineral grand jury finding by a decretal order of our predecessors May 28, and their letter May 2 in answer of Tho. Bushell's Esq; to incourage him to go on in his adventures ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1635C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9055</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827974</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827974</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32400</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65624)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32400)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1900:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Chewton 28 of July, 1658 VVhereas wee of the mineral grand jury finding by a decretal order of our predecessors May 28, and their letter May 2 in answer of Tho. Bushell's Esq; to incourage him to go on in his adventures ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title from caption title and first lines of text.</note>
                  <note>Imprint conjectured by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Jo. Redford for-man of the mineral grand jury there [and 11 others].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Law Library.</note>
                  <note>Wing reel guide incorrectly lists item at 1900:3 as W452B.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bushell, Thomas, 1594-1674 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mines and mineral resources --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:32400:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32400:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <opener>
               <dateline>Chewton <date>28 of July, 1658.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHereas wee of the Mineral grand Jury finding by a decretal Order of our Predeceſſors <hi>May</hi> 28, and their Letter <hi>May</hi> 2 in anſwer of <hi>Tho. Buſhell's</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> to incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him to go on in his adventures for recovering the drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed works of <hi>Rowpits,</hi> which were formerly the deſerted works of Sir <hi>Bevis Bulmar</hi> in the time of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> Reign. And whereas many of the chief Adventurers in the ſaid <hi>Row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits,</hi> do and have conſented to ſurrender not only the one half of their works and Mines there, but likewiſe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption of the other half, paying as much as any other Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant willl give, unto the ſaid <hi>Tho. Buſhell</hi> and his Aſſigns, when the ſaid <hi>Tho. Buſhell</hi> doth make it appear unto the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Court for the time being, that by his and their workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip they be freed from the inundation of their waters. Wee of the grand Jury do Order and confirm the ſaid Decree. And whereas wee find the ſaid <hi>Tho. Buſhell</hi> hath (in relation to his undertakings of recovering their waters) brought it ſo near a probability of perfection, that in time all perſons of known Judgement cannot but conclude the ſame will be done for the general good of thoſe that had formerly ſuffered by thoſe Grooves, and likewiſe a preſident for others to follow the like example, as alſo the certainty of knowing the vaſt riches that lie in <hi>Rowpits</hi> and Green Oare: And whereas wee are informed by the ſaid <hi>Tho. Buſhell</hi> and others, of ſeveral miſdemeanors committed againſt him by turning floods into his ſwallow, to choak and extirpate all his proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſtealing of his tooles from his works, depraving of his Perſon with ſcandalous language, and making new pitches in <hi>Rowpits</hi> before him, ſo ſoon as they ſaw the forefield of Mr. <hi>Buſhell's</hi> Drift from his Swallow had but a vein of ground Oare, 4 foot wide; and 3 fathom high to cheriſh his chargeable undertakings, which uncivill actions of theirs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32400:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->were as we conceive contrary to all equity and good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and in a manner <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Act of Tyranny in as, that Mr. <hi>Buſhell</hi> ſhould drain our waters; and wee ſhould ſuffer ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to take the benefit of new pitches from his adventures, to recover ſuch drowned and forſaken works as the greateſt Engineer hath deſerted, when all perſons have the whole Hill of <hi>Menayp</hi> to make their fortunes by ſuch pitches, as he alledgeth, and not to diſcourage his deſperate undertakings therein by ſuch malitions practices, and eſpecially to ſuch a perſon as Mr. <hi>Buſhell</hi> that is ſent by his Highneſs the Lord Protector, to recover ſuch drowned and deſerted works for the publick good of the Nation, with power to dig, delve, and ſearch in the ſeveral grounds of all his Territories by Letters Patents, paying double treſpaſs, aſ well as in all vaſt Commons, upon hopes from ſuch experiments to eaſe in time the Taxes of the Subject, and to give new birth to the drooping condition of a Miners profeſſion; Wee of the grand Jury of <hi>Chewson</hi> (and other Workmaſters and Miners) for the reaſons. foreſaid, and for preventing any juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints to the Lord Paramount againſt our Lord Royall's Court of <hi>Chewton</hi> for ſuch incivilities to the perſon which his Highneſs hath truſted in that affair, do Order and make this Decree (for the ſaid <hi>Tho. Buſhell's</hi> better incouragement) That from the day of the date of the Order <hi>May</hi> 28, all ſuch new pitches ſhall be void in <hi>Rowpits</hi> and Green oare, but ſuch as the ſaid <hi>Tho. Buſhell</hi> ſhall approve and allow of, and that all former works that have been wrought upon within theſe 5 years, and ſunk 5 fathom deep, to ſtand good by conſent, provided that they keep them lawful, and ſink them to the water, when the ſaid <hi>Tho. Buſhell</hi> is come near them with his Drift of 16 fathom deep by the approbation of this grand Jury, that ſo the wilfulneſs of any malitious perſon might not hinder ſuch a proceed to know the Meanders of thoſe Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Rakes in their deepor ſearch, and the way to go to then recoveries, for their own good afwell as Mr. <hi>Buſhell's</hi> reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the attempt of that great deſign. And whereas the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32400:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
               <hi>ſaid Tho. Buſhell</hi> doth aver, that he never did intend to make it a Mine Royall by his Art and Skill (to the prejudice of us, our Laws and Liberties) as it was reported, unleſs it were againſt the intereſt of ſome croſs-grain'd ſcurrilous fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that will not be governed by our own grand Jury, but rather conteſt with his Highneſs right to <hi>Rowpits,</hi> and bids defiance to prerogative Power, or are back'd by a malitious faction that would hinder the growth of the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacons</hi> Philoſophy in recovering the ſame for the glory of the Nation theſe conſiderations, and at our requeſt to him upon the aforeſaid agreement that he would ſhew his quondam Maſters Philoſophy for recovering <hi>Rowpits</hi> and Green oare from their inundations of water, which is well known to us to be rich in the treaſures of Ledd, and to free other works of greater moment from their contagious damps, that now lie deſerted, on purpoſe that the overplus of their revenew, proceeding from ſuch a deplorable condition, and raiſed by the hand of Providence and Induſtry, might go (as Mr. <hi>Buſhell</hi> did likewiſe aver, upon the word of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman) to charitable uſes of diſcovering richer Mettals expreſt in his late Remonſtrance to his Highneſs, aſ well as by his late Will and Teſtament, for the firſt fruits thereof to ledd the Tower and Schoole in the Church of <hi>Wells.</hi> Wee of the grand Jury do likewiſe make this Order and Decree, That if any miſdemeanor as aforeſaid, ſhall be proved to be done againſt the ſaid <hi>Tho. Buſhell,</hi> his Agents, Servants, or works, ſuch are not only to be baniſhed the occupation upon <hi>Mendyp,</hi> but wee do humbly implore his Highneſs to ſend them to the Mines of <hi>Jamaica,</hi> that they may not infect others, nor bring by their exorbitant corſes more ſcandall upon the whole profeſſion of a Miners innocent calling; ſince we are ſatisfied in our conſciences, that the way of Mr. <hi>Buſhell's</hi> Mineral proceedings, will in this Age bring wonderfull things to paſs, and be admired in the next, for the glory of the Nation, And eſpecially when as the ſaid <hi>Tho. Buſhell</hi> doth aver that he wil tranſport all his rich Weſtern
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32400:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->Mines, lying upon the Sea-ſide, which are or ſhall be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in <hi>Wales, Devon, Cornwall</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> unto the Port or Haven at <hi>Uphill,</hi> to receive their true ſeparations according to the Lord Chancellor <hi>Bacons</hi> Philoſophy, and ſo to be minted in the adjacent City of <hi>Wells</hi> for ſatisfying all returns aſ well as to pay the Miner with his own Coyn, and (without any further ſalary then in one place) to pay the whole of that Commerce.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Jo. Radford</hi> Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of the Mineral Grand Jury there, with his fellows.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Walter Webb.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Franke.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Adams.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jahn Phelps.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Younge.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Dowling.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Alexandor Cuer.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>William Hopkins.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Jonas Lexſtond.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Houſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Ayrer.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
